A Finding Aid to the Robert John Goldwater Papers, 1902-1974, in the Archives of American Art AAA.goldrobe
Archives of American Art
- Writings, 1932-1973; Series 4; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  - Writings by Robert John Goldwater, 1932-1973; 4.1
    - Notes and Bibliographies (Box 3)
      - " Modern Painting, Bibliography of XIX Century Sources", undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Primitive Art, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
        Notes, 5 x 8 cards
      - Redon, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
        Bibliography and notes, 4 x 6 cards
      - "Symbolism, Mainly", undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Vuillard, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
        Bibliography and notes on illustrations, 4 x 6 cards
    - Reviews (Box 4)
      - Book Reviews, 1934-1964, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Exhibition Reviews, 1937-1953 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Talks and Lectures (Box 5)
      - "Anatomizing Abstract Expressionism" (Museum of Modern Art), 1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Art in Times of Crisis (Pontigny), 1944 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Boudin and Homer Lecture (text; research materials, photographs), 1951-1954, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - "Ferdinand Hodler: Naturalism, Symbolism and Ethics" (Guggenheim Museum), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
        Includes 35-mm color slides
      - "Judgments of Primitive Art, 1905-1965" (Berkeley Symposium "Tradition and Creativity in Tribal Art"), 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Klee Lecture, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Modern Art (New School), 1949 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - "Painting and Sculpture" (Cornell), 1954 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Redon Lecture, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Rouault Lecture (Cleveland), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Vuillard Lecture, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Untitled Lectures, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Writings by Other Authors, 1942-circa 1970; 4.2
    - Bourgoies, Jean-Louis, "34 Poems," "Avital Oz's Sculpture 'Dialogue' at O. K. Harris," and "Design for Bewilderment - Labyrinths by Ten Contemporary Artists", undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Goldwater, Clara A. (mother), Poems, 1942-1944, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Seuphor, Michel, "Vincent Van Gogh", circa 1953 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Tuchman, Phyllis, "Bibliography of the Principal Publications of Robert John Goldwater", circa 1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Printed Material, 1931-1974; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 5
  This series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  5.1: Printed Material About/Mentioning Robert John Goldwater, 1939-1974
  5.2: Printed Material By Robert John Goldwater, 1934-1969
  5.3: Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1931-1973
  - Printed Material About/Mentioning Robert John Goldwater, 1939-1974; 5.1
    - Bibliography, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Book Reviews and Book Advertisements, 1939-1946, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Exhibition Catalog ("Robert John Goldwater, A Memorial Exhibition," Museum of Primitive Art), 1974 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Items, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Newspaper Articles, 1939-1947 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Notices of Lectures, Panel Discussions, etc., 1945-1967, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Printed Material by Robert John Goldwater, 1934-1969; 5.2
    - Articles, 1940-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Book, Modern Art In Your Life, with Rene d'Harnoncourt (2nd revised ed.), 1953 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Editorials ( Magazine of Art), 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Exhibition Catalogs (introductions by Goldwater), 1967, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Reviews (book, exhibition, and film), 1934-1969, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1931-1973; 5.3
    - Articles and Reviews, General Art Topics, 1931-1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Exhibition Announcements (Museum of Modern Art 20th Anniversary; Eva Hesse Memorial Exhibition), 1949-1973 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Papers of S. S. Goldwater, M. D., 1902-1956; Series 6; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
  Dr. S. S. Goldwater's professional correspondence documents his work as a hospital administrator in New York City where he served as Superintendent of Mt. Sinai Hospital, Commissioner of Health, and Commissioner of Hospitals.
  - Biographical Information (Box 5)
    - Biographical Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Licenses (medical and drivers), 1902, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - Professional Correspondence, 1909-1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 32-39)
    - Department of Hospitals Correspondence, Vols. I-III, 1934-1940 (Box 5, Folder 40-42)
    - Department of Hospitals Correspondence, Vol. IV, 1934-1940 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Legal Documents (Box 6)
    - Estate Matters, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Will, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Photographs (Clara A. Goldwater [wife] and Robert John Goldwater [son]), 1940s, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Printed Material (Box 6)
    - About/Mentioning S. S. Goldwater, 1914-1956, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - By Clara A. Goldwater, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - By S. S. Goldwater, 1939-1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - City of New York Department of Hospitals, 1935-1936, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Annual reports, miscellaneous items
    - Miscellaneous Subjects, 1925-1941, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Mainly about hospitals and medical topics
    - Obituaries, Family Members, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Obituaries, S. S. Goldwater, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Writings (Box 6)
    - Addresses, 1919-1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Texts, outlines, and notes
    - Notes, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Report, "Preliminary Report Submitted to His Honor, Mayor F. H. LaGuardia by S. S. Goldwater, M. D., Commissioner for the year 1934 - Aims, Activities, Accomplishments, Aids, Impediments, Criticisms" (Box 6, Folder 14)